Hello, and welcome to Lesson 17 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
大家好 欢迎来到Wolfram U的微积分入门课程第17课
The topic for this lesson is the mean value theorem.
本节课的主题是中值定理
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson. The mean value theorem, roughly speaking,
首先 简单介绍一下本课的内容 中值定理 粗略来讲
relates to the slope of an interval with the instantaneous slope of some point in that interval.
与一个区间的斜率以及该区间上某个点的斜率有关
Now let’s look at that a little bit more in detail. Here you’ve got a curve,
接下来看看更详细的情况 这是一条曲线
and I joined the two endpoints over here by a secant. What the theorem is saying is that
将曲线的两个端点用一条割线连接起来 中值定理说的是
the slope of this interval over here is somehow related to the slope of this tangent at some point.
区间的割线斜率与区间上某点的切线斜率之间存在一定的关系
That’s what the theorem is about, about the slopes of intervals and the slopes of tangents.
这就是中值定理的内容 关于区间斜率和切线斜率
The goal of this lesson is to first of all understand the mean value theorem
本节课的目标是 首先理解中值定理
and then give a few applications of the theorem. We’ll begin with
然后给出该定理的一些应用 首先讨论的是
a special case of the theorem called Rolle’s theorem.
该定理的一种特殊情况 称为罗尔定理
As a motivation for Rolle’s theorem, let’s look at the function f[x] = x^2.
为引入罗尔定理 首先考虑函数f[x]=x^2
Here is a plot of the function as a parabola. Notice that the value of the function
图像是一条抛物线 请注意 函数值
at the two endpoints −2 and 2 is the same, and the slope at 0, the derivative, is 0.
在两个端点 -2和2处相等 而在0处的斜率 即导数 为0
That’s the hint for Rolle’s theorem, that the slope is 0 at the top, and you also have a tangent,
这暗示了罗尔定理 顶部割线的斜率0 同时也存在一条切线
so to speak, at which the slope is 0. Now a more formal statement of Rolle’s theorem,
其斜率也为0 接下来对罗尔定理进行更正式的定义
which was proved by Michel Rolle. What it says is that if you have a function
该定理由米歇尔·罗尔证明得到 定理的内容是 如果一个函数
that satisfies three hypotheses—first of all, it is continuous on a certain closed interval;
同时满足三个假设 首先 函数在某个闭区间上连续
it is differentiable on an open interval; and the value of the function at the left endpoint
且在开区间上可微 并且左端点的函数值
is the same as the value at the right endpoint—then there is a number c
与右端点相同 则区间内存在一个c。
in the interval at which the derivative becomes 0. The previous function we talked about in fact
该点导数值为0 实际上 前面提到的函数
satisfies all the three hypotheses. After all, you do have a continuous function,
满足所有三个假设 毕竟 函数是连续的
it’s differentiable and the values at both the end points are the same.
是可微的 并且两个端点处的函数值相等
Here’s a plot which just confirms the theorem and says that the slope of this secant line
这张图 印证了这个定理 并且可以发现 割线
is the same as the slope of that tangent over there, which is 0.
与那条切线的斜率相等 都为0
Okay. Now on to the problems with Rolle’s theorem and how you apply it.
接下来讨论的是使用罗尔定理需要注意的问题以及如何使用罗尔定理
First of all, let’s look at 1/x^2 on the interval (−1, 1). Notice that it has a discontinuity at 0,
首先 观察区间（-1，1）上的1/x^2 注意到其在0处存在间断
so of course it’s not differentiable over there as well.
因此在0处不可微
The values at the endpoints are certainly equal; however, it does not satisfy all the hypotheses of Rolle’s theorem,
区间端点的函数值显然相等 但 这个函数并不满足所有罗尔定理的假设
and hence we cannot guarantee that there is any number in this range at which the slope is 0.
因此 无法确定区间内存在导数值为0的点
In fact, we confirm that using Solve, and we check that the derivative
事实上 利用Solve函数确认了这一点 该区间上的导数
is never 0 in this interval.
永远不为0
As another issue with the theorem, let’s look at the absolute value function between −1 and 1.
罗尔定理另一个需要注意的问题 观察-1和1之间的绝对值函数
Clearly that is continuous, but it is not differentiable at x = 0. There’s a corner at x = 0.
显然函数连续 但x=0处是不可微 x=0处存在拐角
The value of the function at both endpoints is the same, but since it does not satisfy
而区间两个端点的函数值相等 但由于不满足
all the hypotheses of Rolle’s theorem—therefore you cannot guarantee that there is a number at which the slope is 0.
罗尔定理的所有条件 因此 无法确定区间内存在导数值为0的点
Once again, you can use Solve to confirm that there is no such value.
同样地 你可以使用Solve函数进行确认
That’s the derivative of the absolute value function on the interval, and it’s never 0 on that interval.
这是绝对值函数在该区间上的导数 其永远不为0
Okay. Now on to the mean value theorem and some motivation. In the earlier example,
接下来谈谈中值定理及其应用 在前面的例子中
we said that the secant line between −2 and 2 and the tangent line at 0 had the same slope.
-2和2之间的割线与0处的切线具有相同斜率
Now the whole situation over here is very symmetrical, so what we’ll do is we’ll make it
这种情况区间十分对称 接下来将
slightly less symmetrical by looking at the interval [−0.5, 1]. That’s the interval over here.
观察区间变为不那么对称的[-0.5，1] 这是这个区间
Now we notice that the secant line at x = −0.5 and x = 1, the line joining those two points,
注意到 连接x = −0.5和x = 1两点的割线
has got a slope 1/2. We can calculate that. The same thing happens at x = 1/4—namely, the tangent line
斜率为1/2 通过计算 相同的情况出现在x=1/4处 即该点的切线
at that point has a slope of 1/2. The mean value theorem is just a modification,
斜率为1/2 中值定理对罗尔定理进行改变
a more general version of Rolle’s theorem. Here is a formal statement of the theorem which says that
是其更一般的版本 该定理的正式陈述为
suppose you have a function f that is continuous on a closed interval,
函数f在一个闭区间上连续
differentiable on the open interval in that case. Then there is a number c in the interval at which
开区间上可微 那么在该区间上存在一点c 使得
the slope of the tangent line equals the slope of the secant line joining the endpoints.
该点切线斜率等于连接端点的割线斜率
More formally, f'(c) = (f(b) − f(a))/(b − a). Sometimes it’s easier to cross-multiply and get
更正式的表述为 f'(c)=(f(b)-f(a))/(b-a) 有时两边相乘
the same equation in a slightly different form like is done over here. Now of course,
可以等到等式另一种表达形式 如此所示
Rolle’s theorem follows from the mean value theorem because if you set f[b] equal to f[a],
罗尔定理来源于中值定理 如果令f[b]等于f[a]
then you have f'[c] equal to 0 at the point c.
那么在点c处 有f'[c]等于0
That’s the Rolle’s theorem for the sine function on the interval [0, π].
这是对区间[0，π]上正弦函数 应用罗尔定理
There are some issues with the mean value theorem I have interpreted.
前面解释的中值定理中 需要注意一些问题
For example, we could have more than one c, which satisfies the theorem. Here you have a curve
例如 区间上可能存在不止一个满足中值定理的c 这条曲线
in which that’s the secant line and those two tangents have the same slope as the secant line.
这是割线 这两条切线斜率与割线相等
In fact, if you have a constant function like f[x] = 5, then the slope is 0 everywhere.
事实上 像f[x]=5这样的常数函数 切线斜率处处为0
Here’s the constant function 5, and if you plot the function derivative, you see that
这是常数函数5 绘制其导函数 会发现
the theorem is satisfied everywhere. You have some exceptions with the mean value theorem
处处满足中值定理 中值定理存在一些例外特殊情况
when you have either more than one value, or you might even have infinitely many values
即存在一个以上的点 甚至无穷多个点满足定理
because if the slope happens to be 0, then the function must be constant.
因为切线斜率为0 那么函数必然是常数函数
Okay. With that, some applications. For the first application, let’s look at the function x^3 − 8x
有了中值定理 下面是一些应用 第一个应用 函数x^3 - 8x。
on the interval 0 to 4, and you want to find a c in the range which has a tangent line
在0到4的区间上 请在这个范围内找到一个点c
parallel to the secant line to the endpoints. For the first step, you know that the mean value theorem
使得该点切线平行于端点的割线 第一步 中值定理
is certainly applicable because you have a polynomial function. You solve for c or x like this equation,
适用于该问题 因为函数是多项式函数 如这个方程所示 求解出c或者叫x
and the value of c or x is the value of 4/√3. At that value of x,
解得c或x的值为4/√3 函数在点x处
we actually have a tangent line that is parallel to the secant line through the two endpoints.
存在一条切线平行于过两端点的割线
Now let’s check that with the tangent line and a plot of the curve and tangent,
现在我们用切线和曲线和切线的图来检验一下。
and you can see that the secant line over here has the same slope as the tangent line over there.
可见 割线与切线具有相同斜率
Okay. As another example of the mean value theorem, let’s talk about a function f
好的 再举一个关于中值定理的例子 函数f
whose value at 0 is 4 and whose derivative is bounded above by 6, and the question is how large
在0处的值是4 而其导数值不超过6 问题是
can the value of f at 3 possibly be? Because f is differentiable, therefore clearly it is continuous,
f在3处的值可能是多少？因为f是可微的 所以显然它是连续的
and so what we’ll do is we’ll apply the mean value theorem on the interval [0, 3].
接下来在[0，3]区间上应用中值定理
The mean value theorem says that you have the equation f(3) − f(0) is the value of the derivative
根据中值定理 有f(3)-f(0)等于
at that point c times (3 − 0). You have a c with that property. Because you have f' less than
区间上一点c处的导数乘以(3 - 0) 存在一点c具有这样的特性 又因为f'小于
or equal to 6, therefore you set up the equation, which is f'[c], to be at most 6 and solve it for f[3],
或等于6 列出方程 f'[c]不大于6 求解出f[3]
and you find that the value of f[3] can be at the most 22.
得到f[3]的值最大为22
Okay. As another example, let’s try and show that this polynomial, x^3 + 8x − 2, has exactly one root.
再举一个例子 试着证明多项式x^3 + 8x - 2 正好有一个根
Because the function is continuous, you can apply the intermediate value theorem to try and show
由于函数是连续的 可以尝试应用中值定理进行证明
that a root exists. The point is that the value of f at 0 is negative and the value at 1 is positive,
只存在一个根 问题的关键在于 f在0处的函数值为负 在1处的函数值为正
so the function must take every value between those two values, so at some point or the other,
由于函数必然取遍这两点之间的值 所以在区间内的某点处
it must become 0, so you certainly have a root in the interval 0 to 1.
函数值必为0 所以 可以肯定在0到1的区间内有一个根
Now let’s suppose there are two roots, a and b. Then the mean value theorem would say
接下来假设存在两个根 a和b 利用中值定理
that you actually have a slope of 0 between them, and hence you have a point c
a和b之间存在一点切线斜率为0 即存在一点c
for which the slope is 0 as well. Then if we look at the derivative, it’s 3x^2 + 8,
该点切线斜率为0 原函数的导数为3x^2+8。
which can never be 0, so it’s clear that you only have one root,
导数永远不可能是0 所以 明显地 方程有且只有一个根
but let’s just plot the function and make sure. You see over here that the function
将函数图像画出来 确保正确 请看这里 函数
becomes zero somewhere to the right of 0, but then never again.
在0的右侧某处变成零 后面再也不等于0
Now as an amusing application of the mean value theorem, let’s talk about speed limits.
下面是中值定理的一个有趣应用 讨论的是限速问题
Suppose you’ve got two points, A and B, on a road, and they are 90 miles apart.
假设路上的两个点 A和B 两点相距90英里
You start from point A at noon. Suppose you don’t take any breaks in your journey,
你在中午时分从点A出发 假设在路途中没有任何休息
and you get to the point B at 1 o’clock. Now, the speed limit in that area says that
在一点钟到达B点B 该地区的限速规定是
you cannot exceed 80 miles per hour. The question is should you receive a speeding ticket or not?
不能超过80英里每小时 请问你该不该收到超速罚单？
Well, here’s the average speed for the whole trip. It’s 90. If you apply the mean value theorem,
整段行程的平均速度为90英里 应用中值定理
at some point, you must surely have crossed the speed limit of 80 miles per hour,
在某些时刻 你肯定超过了时速80英里的限制
so certainly you should receive a speeding ticket, and it’s going to cost you some money.
因此你肯定会收到一张超速罚单 花去一些钱
Okay. Let’s summarize the lesson for today. We saw that the mean value theorem relates
好的 我们来总结一下本次课程 中值定理涉及
the average slope of an interval with the instantaneous slope in the interval. Basically it says that
区间的割线斜率与区间某点处的斜率 总的来说
you’ve got a point at which the average slope is the same as the instantaneous slope.
中值定理能得到割线斜率与某点处的切线斜率相等
Of course this theorem is a very useful theorem. We saw some applications,
这个定理非常有用 我们也讨论了它的一些应用
but in the next lesson, we’ll see even more where we’ll talk about the graphs of functions.
在下一节课 我们会看到更多应用中值定理的地方 将讨论函数的图像
That’s really a very interesting geometrical problem which gets solved nicely
函数图像是非常有趣的几何问题 该问题
with the use of the mean value theorem and other properties of derivatives.
利用中值定理和导数的其他性质能得到很好的解决
But before we do that, do look over today’s lesson, do review the exercises
在此之前 请回顾本次课程 务必复习习题
and be ready for the lesson on graphs of functions. I’ll stop over here. Thank you.
并准备好关于函数图像的课程 本次课到此结束 谢谢！